<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<dt-type group="dt">
	<name>row-selector</name>
	<summary>Selector options for rows.</summary>

	<description>
<![CDATA[

The DataTables `dt-api rows()` and `dt-api row()` (also optionally `dt-api cells()` and `dt-api cell()`) methods provide the ability to select rows from the table. What rows are selected and how the selector actually operates is controlled by this `dt-type row-selector` data type.

### Options

The row selector can be given in a number of different forms, to make it easy to apply to your data and use case:

* No selector - Select all rows
* `dt-type integer` - Row index selector
* `dt-type string` - jQuery selector
* `dt-type node` - `dt-tag tr` element selector
* `dt-type jQuery` - jQuery object of row nodes
* `dt-type array` - Array containing any combination of the above options


## No selector

If no selector is given (more specifically `dt-type undefined`), then all rows are selected.

###### Get data for all rows in the table:

```js
var table = $('#example').DataTable();
var allData = table.rows().data();
```


## integer

DataTables stores each row internally with a row index for fast look up of row information. When the selector is given as an integer, this value represents a row index (`dt-api rows().indexes()` / `dt-api row().index()`).

###### Row index 0 data:

```js
var table = $('#example').DataTable();
var data = table.row( 0 ).data();
```

###### Find data using row indexes:

```js
var table = $('#example').DataTable();

// Find indexes of rows which have `Yes` in the second column
var indexes = table.rows().eq( 0 ).filter( function (rowIdx) {
	return table.cell( rowIdx, 1 ).data() === 'Yes' ? true : false;
} );

// Add a class to those rows using an index selector
table.rows( indexes )
	.nodes()
	.to$()
	.addClass( 'highlight' );
```


## string

When the selector is given as a string, it is treated as a [jQuery selector](http://api.jquery.com/category/selectors/) that operates on the `dt-tag tr` elements in the table. For full information about the options available for jQuery selectors, please refer to the [jQuery selector documentation](http://api.jquery.com/category/selectors/).

Note that just like jQuery selector, is it possible to supply multiple selectors using comma separated notation (i.e. just separate by a comma) when the selector is provided as a string.

###### Select a single row by id:

```js
var table = $('#example').DataTable();
var row = table.row('#row-42');
```

###### Select rows by class name:

```js
var table = $('#example').DataTable();
var rows = table.rows('.priority');
```

###### Select rows by two class name selectors:

```js
var table = $('#example').DataTable();
var rows = table.rows('.important, .intermediate');
```


## node

`dt-tag tr` DOM elements can be given as a row selector to select a row in the DataTabels API from that DOM element. This can be useful for getting data from a row, or performing other row based operations, when you have only the DOM node for reference, for example in an event handler.

###### Get the data for a row that was clicked upon:

```js
var table = $('#example').DataTable();

$('#example tbody').on( 'click', 'tr', function () {
  var rowData = table.row( this ).data();
  // ... do something with `rowData`
} );
```


## jQuery

Very similar to the above `node` type (since a jQuery object is an _array-like_ list of DOM nodes), a jQuery instance can be given as a row selector, with any nodes which are selected by jQuery and match those available in the table selected.

###### Get data from rows in a jQuery instance:

```js
var rows = $('tr.immediate');
var table = $('#example').DataTable();

var rowData = table.rows( rows ).data();
```


## array

Any combination of the above options can be given as selector together, providing a method to select multiple rows, or to mix selector types, by simply providing the selector options you want in an array.

###### Get the data for two rows, based on id:

```js
var table = $('#example').DataTable();
var data = table.rows( ['#row-42', '#row-91'] ).data();
```

###### Mix `row-selector` types - id and class selector

```js
var table = $('#example').DataTable();
var data = table.rows( ['#row-42', '.important'] ).data();
```


]]>
	</description>
</dt-type>