<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<dt-page order="5" comments="yes" main-nav="yes">
	<title>Foundation</title>

	<summary>
	<![CDATA[

[Foundation](http://foundation.zurb.com) from Zurb is a CSS framework that allows rapid development of complex sites, featuring a mobile first approach to the design process for HTML pages. With Foundation you can create beautiful, complex and customisable sites / apps very quickly, and with the DataTables integration for Foundation your tables will have all of the options DataTables provides as well.

	]]>
	</summary>

	<content>
	<![CDATA[

[Foundation](http://foundation.zurb.com) from Zurb is a CSS framework that allows rapid development of complex sites, featuring a mobile first approach to the design process for HTML pages. Using a CSS framework such as Foundation gives you the ability to create a user interface with a unified look and feel very quickly. And DataTables can be integrated directly with Foundation to ensure that it fits into the flow of your site / app perfectly!

Foundation provides a [number of options](http://foundation.zurb.com/docs/components/tables.html) for styling HTML tables. The DataTables / Foundation integration ensures that you can use all of these features as well as the enhancements that DataTables makes to a plain HTML table.


## Installation

To have DataTables styled by Foundation, all you need to do, as well as including the DataTables core Javascript file on your page, is include the DataTables / Foundation CSS and Javascript integration files. These files simply alter the DataTables defaults, such as class names to use the names used by Foundation, and add styling information specific to DataTables.

Both files are both available on the DataTables CDN (below) or you can obtain these files directly from the [DataTables integration plug-ins repository on GitHub](https://github.com/DataTables/Plugins/tree/master/integration/foundation).

<div class="cdn">
	<span>CSS</span>
	<input type="text" value="//cdn.datatables.net/plug-ins/{plugins-release-version}/integration/foundation/dataTables.foundation.css" readonly>
</div>

<div class="cdn">
	<span>JS</span>
	<input type="text" value="//cdn.datatables.net/plug-ins/{plugins-release-version}/integration/foundation/dataTables.foundation.js" readonly>
</div>


## Example

An example of a DataTable styled by Foundation is shown below.

<iframe border="0" frameBorder="0" src="foundation-simple.html" width="100%" height="520"></iframe>
<p><a href="foundation-simple.html" target="_blank">View example in a new window.</a></p>

	]]>
	</content>
</dt-page>