<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<dt-page order="6" comments="yes" main-nav="yes">
	<title>jQuery UI</title>

	<summary>
	<![CDATA[

[jQuery UI](//jqueryui.com) is a popular suite of Javascript widgets and provides a common styling framework for these widgets through its [ThemeRoller](//jqueryui.com/themeroller/) component. DataTables integration for jQuery UI provides the ability to have DataTables enhanced tables styled in the same way as other jQuery UI components, providing a common look and feel for your site if you are already using jQuery UI.

	]]>
	</summary>

	<content>
	<![CDATA[

[jQuery UI](//jqueryui.com) is a popular suite of Javascript widgets such as [DatePicker](//jqueryui.com/datepicker/), [AutoComplete](//jqueryui.com/autocomplete/) and [Dialog](//jqueryui.com/dialog/). Although jQuery UI isn't a CSS framework in the same sense as [Bootstrap](bootstrap) or [Foundation](foundation) it does provide a common styling framework for its widgets through its [ThemeRoller](//jqueryui.com/themeroller/) component.

DataTales provides integration files which can be used to have tables styled in the same manner as other jQuery UI widgets, ensuring a consistent look-and-feel across components on your site / app, if you are already using jQuery UI. DataTables augments the ThemeRoller provided CSS with information for styling the DataTables enhanced tables since ThemeRoller does not provide this information, and as such, you can use the same [styling classes](classes) as with the default DataTables CSS.


## Installation

To have DataTables styled in the same manner as other jQuery UI widgets, all you need to do, as well as including the DataTables core Javascript file on your page, is include the DataTables / jQuery UI CSS and Javascript integration files.

Both files are both available on the DataTables CDN (below) or you can obtain these files directly from the [DataTables integration plug-ins repository on GitHub](https://github.com/DataTables/Plugins/tree/master/integration/jqueryui).

<div class="cdn">
	<span>CSS</span>
	<input type="text" value="//cdn.datatables.net/plug-ins/{plugins-release-version}/integration/jqueryui/3/dataTables.jqueryui.css" readonly">
</div>

<div class="cdn">
	<span>JS</span>
	<input type="text" value="//cdn.datatables.net/plug-ins/{plugins-release-version}/integration/jqueryui/3/dataTables.jqueryui.js" readonly">
</div>


## Example

An example of a DataTable styled by jQuery UI is shown below.

<iframe border="0" frameBorder="0" src="jqueryui-simple.html" width="100%" height="510"></iframe>
<p><a href="jqueryui-simple.html" target="_blank">View example in a new window.</a></p>


## Legacy support

DataTables actually has jQuery UI support directly integrated into the core Javascript through the `dt-init jQueryUI` option. However, this option is depreciated in DataTables 1.10 and will be removed in 1.11 in favour of the method described on this page which is more modular and matches how the integration is provided for other CSS frameworks such as [Bootstrap](bootstrap) and [Foundation](foundation). As such, it is recommended that you make use of the jQuery UI integration files provided here, rather than the `dt-init jQueryUI` option.


	]]>
	</content>
</dt-page>