<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<dt-api group="cells">
	<name>cell()</name>
	<summary>Select a single cell from a table.</summary>
	<since>1.10</since>

  <type type="function">
    <signature>cell( [ modifier ] )</signature>
    <description>Select a cell that matches the modifier</description>
    <parameter type="selector-modifier" name="modifier" default="">
      Option used to specify how the cells should be ordered, and if paging or filtering in the table should be taken into account.
    </parameter>
    <returns type="DataTables.Api">DataTables API instance with selected cell</returns> 
  </type>
	<type type="function">
		<signature>cell( cellSelector, [ modifier ] )</signature>
		<description>Select the cell found by a cell selector</description>
		<parameter type="cell-selector" name="cellSelector">
			Cell selector.
		</parameter>
		<parameter type="selector-modifier" name="modifier" default="">
			Option used to specify how the cells should be ordered, and if paging or filtering in the table should be taken into account.
		</parameter>
		<returns type="DataTables.Api">DataTables API instance with selected cell</returns>
	</type>
	<type type="function">
		<signature>cell( rowSelector, columnSelector, [ modifier ] )</signature>
		<description>Select the cell found from both row and column selectors</description>
		<parameter type="row-selector" name="rowSelector">
			Row selector, used to specify which row the cell should be taken from.
		</parameter>
		<parameter type="column-selector" name="columnSelector">
			Column selector, used to specify which column the cell should be taken from.
		</parameter>
		<parameter type="selector-modifier" name="modifier" default="">
			Option used to specify how the cells should be ordered, and if paging or filtering in the table should be taken into account.
		</parameter>
		<returns type="DataTables.Api">DataTables API instance with selected cell</returns>
	</type>

	<description>
		Select an individual cell to work with from a DataTable, with its chained methods providing the ability to get / set the data in the cell, work with it node directly and other actions.

		Note that this method selects a single cell. If the selectors provided resolve to multiple cells in this method, the result will be truncated to just a single cell - the first one found. If you need to work with multiple cells, the `dt-api cells()` method is available with the same selection options.

		The method has two forms, reflecting the fact the cells can be selected in multiple different ways as your implementation demands:

		* Cell selector
		* Cross product between row and column selectors
	</description>

	<example title=""><![CDATA[
]]></example>

	<related type="api">cells()</related>
</dt-api>
