<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<dt-api group="core">
	<name>columns().search.fixed()</name>
	<summary>Get / set a named search to apply to a column.</summary>
	<since>2.0</since>

	<type type="function">
		<signature>columns().search.fixed()</signature>
		<description>
			Get a list of the names of searches applied to the selected columns.
		</description>
		<returns type="DataTable.Api">
			An API instance that contains the names of the search terms applied to the columns.
		</returns>
	</type>

	<type type="function">
		<signature>columns().search.fixed( name )</signature>
		<description>
			Get the search term used for the given name.
		</description>
		<returns type="undefined|function|string|RegExp">
			The search term that was originally applied.
		</returns>
	</type>

	<type type="function">
		<signature>columns().search.fixed( name, searchTerm [, options ] )</signature>
		<description></description>
		<parameter type="string" name="name">
			Treat as a regular expression (`true`) or not (default, `false`).
		</parameter>
		<parameter type="string|RegExp|function|null" name="input">
			The search term to apply to the table.

			Use `null` for this value to delete an existing search term.

			If given as a string, it will be applied to the table's search using DataTables "smart" search (see `-api search()`).

			If working with a regular expression, the data given is the search data for the cells in column in question.
			
			In the case of a function the function is called for each row with the follow parameters passed in:
			
			1. The search string of data from all searchable columns in the table
			2. The row's original data object
			3. The row's data index
			4. Array of the column indexes included in the search (DataTables 3+). Note that if a single column is selected, this parameter will be a number, rather than an array.
			
			A boolean value should be returned: `true` to keep the row, `false` to filter it out.
		</parameter>
		<parameter type="DataTable.SearchOptions" name="options" default="{}" since="3.0.0">
			Configuration options for how the search will be performed. See `-type DataTable.SearchOptions` for a description of all options. If an option is not given here, the value that it was set to for the previous search will be used, or the defaults is no previous search.

			The value of this parameter is used only when a string based search is provided for the previous parameter. This value is ignored if a regular expression or function is provided.
		</parameter>
		<returns type="DataTable.Api">DataTables API instance</returns>
	</type>

	<description>
		<![CDATA[
		< Backwards compatibility note: In DataTables 2 and earlier, this method would assign the provided search term to all columns that were selected - i.e. it does an AND search. From DataTables 3, the search performs is as single search across all columns - i.e. it is an OR search.

		Just as `-api search.fixed()` applies a "fixed" search term to the whole table, this method can be used to apply a search term to a subset of columns in the table.

		The fixed search (which might also be termed _sticky_ or _named_ searches) provides a way to easily add cumulative search terms to the table. You can add multiple independent search terms, and DataTables will combine them (AND logic) displaying the result of all search terms that have been applied.

		Please be aware that this method sets the fixed search to apply to the columns only - it does not actually perform the search. In order to have the search performed and the result shown, use the `-api draw()` method, which can be called simply as a chained method of this method.

		Furthermore, fixed search logic is not automatically included in the DataTables state object (`-api state()`). If you wish to have a fixed search saved in a state, you must use `-event stateSaveParams` and `-event stateLoadParams`.

		When using server-side processing, additional logic must be added at the server-side to handle fixed search terms. Additionally, searching by functions is not possible, since the search function is client-side based.
		]]>
	</description>

	<example title="Get the search term applied to all columns (no selector)"><![CDATA[
let table = new DataTable('#myTable');

let searchTerm = table
	.columns()
	.search.fixed();
]]></example>

	<example title="Get an search term for a subset of columns"><![CDATA[
let search = table.columns([1, 4]).search.fixed('mySearch');
]]></example>

	<example title="Applying a search string"><![CDATA[
table.columns('.cities').search.fixed('myString', 'Paris');
]]></example>

	<example title="Applying a search regex to column indexes 0 and 1"><![CDATA[
table.columns([0, 1]).search.fixed('myRegex', /l.*n/i);
]]></example>

	<example title="Applying a search function to multiple columns"><![CDATA[
table.columns('.number').search.fixed('myFunc', (cell, data) => {
	return cell > 50;
});
]]></example>

	<example title="Deleting an existing search term from all columns"><![CDATA[
table.columns().search.fixed('mySearch', null);
]]></example>

	<related>-init searching</related>
	<related>-init columns.searchable</related>
	<related>-api search()</related>
	<related>-api search.fixed()</related>
	<related>-api column().search()</related>
	<related>-api column().search.fixed()</related>
	<related>-api columns().search()</related>
	<related>-api columns().search.fixed()</related>
</dt-api>