<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<dt-api group="columns">
	<name>columns().order()</name>
	<summary>Order the table by the selected columns.</summary>
	<since>1.10</since>

	<type type="function" since="2.0.0">
		<signature>columns().order()</signature>
		<description>Determine if the table is being ordered by the selected columns.</description>
		<returns type="DataTables.Api">DataTables API instance containing `-string asc`, `-string desc` or an empty string (indicating index data order) for the possible ordering applied to each column selected. If a selected column is not being ordered on, `null` is given.</returns>
	</type>

	<type type="function">
		<signature>columns().order( direction )</signature>
		<description>Order the table, in the direction specified, by the columns selected by the `-api columns()` selector.</description>
		<parameter type="string" name="direction">
			Direction of sort to apply to the selected columns - `dt-string desc` (descending) or `dt-string asc` (ascending). Note this one direction is applied to all columns from the selector.
		</parameter>
		<returns type="DataTables.Api">DataTables API instance</returns>
	</type>

	<description>
		This method provides a useful alternative to the `-api order()` method, allowing you to select the columns that you want to be ordered using the flexible `-api columns()` selector and having them ordered in the direction specified. As of v2 it also allows you to obtain ordering information about the selected columns - determining if they are used in the current order of the table and what ordering direction.

		Multi-column ordering is achieved by ensuring that the column selector matches multiple columns (single column ordering is performed if only one column is matched, or by using the `-api column().order()` method). The order of the matched columns defines the priority sequence in which the ordering of the table is applied.

		Please be aware that when used as a setter this method sets the ordering to apply to the table - it does not actually perform the order. To have the ordering performed, use the `-api draw()` method, which can be called simply as a chained method of the `-api order()` method's returned object - for example `table.order([0, 'desc']).draw();`.
	</description>

	<example title="Sort by all columns with the class '.status'"><![CDATA[
var table = new DataTable('#myTable');

table
	.columns('.status')
	.order('desc')
	.draw();
]]></example>

	<related>-init order</related>
	<related>-init ordering</related>
	<related>-api order()</related>
	<related>-api column().order()</related>
</dt-api>