<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<dt-api group="tables">
	<name>table().header.structure()</name>
	<summary>Get a JavaScript representation of the table header structure</summary>
	<since>2.0</since>

	<type type="function">
		<signature>table().header.structure( [ columns ] )</signature>
		<description>
			Get the structure of the table header
		</description>
		<parameter name="columns" type="column-selector" default="undefined">
			Select which columns to get the header cells for. By default all columns in the table (regardless of visibility) will be retrieved.
		</parameter>
		<returns type="array">
			An array of arrays containing objects and null values that describe the header structure. See the description for full details.
		</returns>
	</type>

	<description>
	<![CDATA[
		This method provides the ability to get a JavaScript native representation of the HTML structure of the table's header. It allows for complex headers (i.e. cells with `colspan` and `rowspan` attributes) and multi-row headers.

		The data structure returned has a top level array with one entry for each row in the header. Each row entry is an array of objects or a null value. The object structure is used to describe a table cell and has the following properties:

		* `colspan` - The number of columns that the cell spans over
		* `cell` - The HTML element for the cell (`-tag th` or `-tag td`)
		* `rowspan` - The number of rows that the cell spans
		* `title` - The title text for the cell.

		A `null` value in place of the object represents a cell that has another spanning into it due to the rowspan or colspan attributes of the previous cells.

		As an example, consider the following HTML for a table header:

		```html
		<thead>
			<tr>
				<th rowspan="2" width="15%">Name</th>
				<th colspan="2">Position</th>
				<th colspan="3">Contact</th>
			</tr>
			<tr>
				<th colspan="3" data-dt-order="disable">HR info</th>
				<th colspan="2">Direct</th>
			</tr>
		</thead>
		```

		When read through this method, the result would be:

		```js
		[
			[
				{colspan: 1, rowspan: 2, cell: <th>, title: 'Name'},
				{colspan: 2, rowspan: 1, cell: <th>, title: 'Position'},
				null,
				{colspan: 3, rowspan: 1, cell: <th>, title: 'Contact'},
				null,
				null
			],
			[
				null,
				{colspan: 3, rowspan: 1, cell: <th>, title: 'HR info'},
				null,
				null,
				{colspan: 2, rowspan: 1, cell: <th>, title: 'Direct'},
				null
			]
		]
		```
	]]>
	</description>

	<related>-api table().header()</related>
	<related>-api table().footer()</related>
	<related>-api table().header.structure()</related>
	<related>-api table().footer.structure()</related>
</dt-api>
