<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<dt-page comments="yes" order="9">
	<title>9. JS Bin</title>

	<summary>
	<![CDATA[

DataTables.net has a custom install of [JS Bin](http://jsbin.com) available at [http://live.datatables.net](http://live.datatables.net) which is customised to meet the needs of rapidly developing and testing code for DataTables. With JS Bin you can easily try out a option or API method and provide test cases when submitting issues.

	]]>
	</summary>

	<content>
	<![CDATA[

When working with DataTables it can often be useful to try code out in a simple test environment to evaluate a particular feature or perhaps to locate a problem in existing code. To make this process of building simple test cases as easy as possible we have a custom install of [JS Bin](http://jsbin.com) which features customisations specific to DataTables.

JS Bin is a web-app that allows input of Javascript, HTML and CSS that is then run in the browser. You can save Bins to share with others. It is an [open source program](http://jsbin.tumblr.com/about), developed by [Remy Sharp](http://remysharp.com/) of [Left Logic](http://leftlogic.com/) and others and we owe them huge thanks for making this fantastic tool available to us!

JS Bin is particularly useful for DataTables when:

* Submitting a question in the [forums](/forums) to provide a test case showing the problem.
* When I answer an issue with a running code snippet
* Simply trying out a specific option or API method.



## Using JS Bin

Actually using JS Bin is very simply, simply load [http://live.datatables.net](http://live.datatables.net) in your browser and start customising the HTML / Javascript / CSS as required. The buttons at the top of the browser window allow you to select what code is shown, and an option to see the final output.

To share a created bin click the _Share_ menu at the top of the browser window and copy the URL shown. Simply add that URL to your forum post, e-mail or otherwise share it and other developers will be able to review your example.

### Libraries / extras

One of the customisations made for the DataTables JS Bin is to provide the ability to directly include DataTables core files and its [extras](/extras). To use a specific version of DataTables or an extras, simply select the _Add library_ menu at the top of the browser and the required code will be added to the document.

If you are looking for a specific version of DataTables or an extras which is not shown in the _Add library_ menu, the code can be found on the [DataTables CDN](//cdn.datatables.net) and included from there.



## Ajax loaded data

When working with the DataTables JS Bin it is often useful to have Ajax data available to work with, all of the Ajax data used in the [Ajax](/examples/ajax) and [server-side processing](/examples/server_side) examples are available for building test cases.

### Ajax

The Ajax data used in the DataTables [Ajax examples](/examples/ajax) can be included from `dt-path /ajax` or `dt-path /examples/ajax/data` (the former is simply an alias for the later). The files available include are:

* `dt-path arrays.txt` - Array of arrays data source ([example](http://live.datatables.net/ajax-data-source/1/edit))
* `dt-path objects.txt` - Array of objects data source ([example](http://live.datatables.net/ajax-objects/1/edit))
* `dt-path orthogonal.txt` - Array of object with orthogonal data ([example](http://live.datatables.net/ajax-orthogonal/1/edit))

### Server-side processing

The scripts used for the [server-side processing examples](/examples/server_side) can be included from `dt-path /ssp` or `dt-path /examples/server_side/scripts` (the former is simply an alias for the later). The scripts available include are:

* `dt-path server_processing.txt` - Array of arrays data source ([example](http://live.datatables.net/ssp-arrays/1/))
* `dt-path objects.txt` - Array of objects data source ([example](http://live.datatables.net/ssp-objects/1/))
* `dt-path post.txt` - Using HTTP _POST_ data ([example](http://live.datatables.net/ssp-post/1/))
* `dt-path ids-objects.txt` - Adding IDs to rows automatically with object based data ([example](http://live.datatables.net/ssp-ids/1/)).



## Registration

JS Bin provides the ability to register to sign in with a [GitHub account](https://github.com/). This provides the ability to view your saved Bins for later retrieval.

The DataTables JS Bin does not current interface with your DataTables account.

	]]>
	</content>
</dt-page>